I cannot help but be moved by the biblical truths that this little lesson contain, this track contain, and so I gratefully acknowledge whatever good there might be in this lesson I owe to Brother David Roper, and whatever bad there is in this lesson I owe to myself.
But the lesson brings into focus very sharply the limitations that we must impose upon human language, or rather that are imposed upon human language.
For if it was possible for me this morning to have a full command of the words and the moods and the shades of meaning to express vividly the ideas, and ideas are just mental images of the lesson of the truth that this lesson contain,
there isn't a single person that will leave this building this morning without being firmly dedicated to the service of God.
Now I don't expect that to happen. I don't expect that everyone that is here this morning will leave this building firmly dedicated to the service of God.
But that sad fact is simply owing to the limitations that we must cope with in trying to express our thoughts.
The lesson is a narration of a story. I'm going to tell you a story. The names in the story are assumed names, but the characters may well represent someone that you know, and alas they may well represent you or they may well represent me.
The story is about a man, and we'll call him John.
Just because John is a common name, we'll call him John Jones. The name could be your name or mine.
But we'll call him John, and the story begins on a Monday morning in the autumn months.
John is awakened early. He is awakened by a beam of sunlight, autumn sunlight.
And John feels rested and relaxed even though it's an hour earlier than his usual time for a rising to go to work.
And he thinks that since it is a beautiful, warm autumn morning, and there won't be many more days such as this before bad weather sets in, that he will walk to work.
So he gets up and dresses quietly and quickly.
And as he drinks his morning coffee, he gazes in upon the sleeping form of his wife, Mary.
And he smiles as he sees how comfortably she sleeps and takes her rest.
And John Jones, as he leans his hand against the post of the bedroom door, he thinks how wonderful you are, Mary, and how thankful I am that God has given me a wife like you.
Strange that John Jones should be thinking thoughts like this because John isn't a servant of God.
John is not a Christian.
But his wife, Mary, she is a Christian.
But John has never come around yet to the point of obeying the Lord.
And as he gazes in upon her, he thinks how wonderful you are, Mary.
And I am thankful that God has given me a wife like you.
And I know that there isn't a single phase of your life that your faith has not influenced.
And you are what you are because you are a Christian.
And I love you for that.
And as he turns from that door, he gazes in upon the sleeping form of his little boy, Billy.
And he smiles as he sees how soundly he sleeps, how he snores, and how soundly he sleeps just before the awakening hours of the morning.
And once again, this feeling of gratitude and this feeling of cry crept over John Jones that this was his little boy.
And then he turns from that door and he looks in upon the sleeping figure of his little girl, Susie.
And John Jones knew that God had been good to him.
Good to him despite the fact that John Jones had given nothing back unto God.
Funny that he should be thinking thoughts like this.
And as he walks out the door and fills his lungs with a warm autumn air, he thinks it's good to be alive.
It is good to be alive.
And the world is quiet.
There are no sounds except the thrilling symphony of the sounds of the songs of a thousand birds that thrust forth their songs of gratitude and praise to the maker.
And John, why can't you understand?
And as he looks down the street which he lives on, he sees all the beautiful leaves on the trees, all the different shades of red and green.
And there's still green in the trees.
And there's all the different shades of yellow and orange and all glistening and shining in the bright autumn sun.
And John, why can't you understand that this is perhaps an omen, a message?
John, why can't you see that all of nature is dying, that it is going to sleep?
And John, why can't you see that a dying nature depicts a dying humanity?
And John doesn't think of the fact that all of nature is going to sleep, dying.
And he does not think of the fact that he himself may die someday.
The world is quiet before the invading army of breadwinners like John.
There are no screaming children playing in the street.
There are no housewives chattering across the back fence.
And the air is pure from the putrefied influence of burnt gasoline that will soon be burrowed in from the army of automobiles that will be invaded in the streets and boulevards.
And it is a quiet, beautiful morning.
And John Jones is alive and he is happy.
And he is grateful to be alive.
And as he begins his walk down the sidewalk, his thoughts go back to how good God has been to him.
And he remembered a sermon he heard.
When was it?
Was it last Sunday?
No, no, it wasn't last Sunday because that was yesterday.
And I remember when little Susie came in to ask me and to beg me to go to church.
And I remember I told her that I was tired.
And then I realized I wasn't tired because I had slept an hour longer this morning because it was Sunday morning.
Then I told her, well, Daddy has to do some work around the house.
Susie, you go on with Mother.
And I have to do some work around the house.
I have to, let's see, oh, yes, I have to clean and paint the rain gutters before bad weather comes.
And then John smiled somewhat shamefully as he remembered the excuse that he had made to his little girl.
And he remembered how Billy had wanted to stay home too because Daddy stayed home.
But he remembered he had on occasion gone to church and he had seen there seated in the pews in a row the Lemons family, the Curry family, and the Lowens family.
And he thought how wonderful this theme that father and mother and children would all sit together, they would listen and learn together.
And once again this feeling of John was face to face with the realization that he was letting his family down, that he was letting his God down, that he was neglecting important things.
But he remembered he had heard a sermon two or three Sundays ago back in August when the preacher had preached on the judgment.
And he remembered when he had read from 2 Peter and he had said that the earth and all of its works shall be burnt up.
And John didn't like to believe that.
And as he walked along, he deliberately planted his feet upon a section of sidewalk and said,
This has been here for years and years.
It is too everlasting.
And then he walked down the street a little bit further and he came to a section of the sidewalk that was cracked.
It was broken.
And John said, Well, after he thought for a moment, I suppose that the most durable things that are material can fade away.
And then he continued his walk on down the sidewalk.
And as he passed the home of the Currys, he saw Mrs. Curry stick her head out the door.
And she looked both ways.
And John stopped for a moment and smiled.
It was no doubt that she had just gotten up.
She still, her hair was a mess and she still had her robe on.
And she looked both ways up and down the street thinking that no one was looking.
She sneaked out on the porch and got the paper and went back in the house again.
And John walked on down the sidewalk.
It is just a world that is coming alive.
And John Jones is alive and he is grateful.
And as he walked down the sidewalk, he could smell the odor of bacon frying across the street coming from the Ingrams' home.
And parked by the curb was a car all decorated with ribbons and crepe papers.
And placards were printed on the car.
And he had remembered that the previous Saturday, the Ingram girl had married the Williams boy and they had flown away to California on their honeymoon.
John, why can't you understand that in Matthew 24, that as in the days of Noah, they were marrying and giving him marriage.
And so shall it be when the Son of Man shall come.
As in the days before the flood, they were eating and drinking.
These are warnings, John.
Why can't you understand them?
And he walks on and he hears the steady, resting tones of a man's voice speaking.
And he realizes that this is across the street coming from a little white house that sits back off the road where old man Glazer lives.
The old fellow lives all alone.
And he is hard of hearing.
And he has his radio turned up loud in case.
And the morning news is on.
And he heard the commentator say that during the night that Iran and Israel and Palestine and Iraq, the leaders had gotten together and they had discussed and negotiated peace talks.
And it seemed like once again the world was going to enjoy peace.
John, why can't you remember a passage from Paul in 1 Thessalonians, the 5th verse.
When they are saying peace and safety, then come a sudden destruction upon them as prevaileth upon a woman with child.
And they shall in no wise assume peace.
But John never dreamed that.
As he walks on down the street, he steps alive with youth, his raincoat over his arm in case the day should bring showers.
John is still musing over how good it is to be alive.
And as he passes the neat trimmed houses, he is grateful for God.
He is grateful for country and for job and for luxury and for family.
He is grateful for so many things.
And yet the same nagging, accusing thought kept occurring to John.
John, you have done nothing about these things.
You have done nothing.
And then John realized, John Jones, you're going to have to do something to show God that you're grateful for all this.
You're going to have to obey your Lord.
You're going to have to obey him and show him that you're grateful for all of these things.
When are you going to do it, John?
Well, I can't this Wednesday night.
That's the night that me and the fellas go bowling.
And, well, maybe Sunday I'll go.
And, no, no, that's the weekend that Jerry and I had planned to get one more fishing trip in before bad weather comes along.
And one of these days, I'm going to obey the gospel.
I'm going to show God.
And then he stopped at the corner of Oak Street to let the Coca-Cola truck pass that was making his deliveries.
And John was musing over what he should do, what he was going to do, and what he intended to do someday soon.
And then he resumes his walk after the Coca-Cola truck passed.
And John was just raising his foot to put it up on the curb when it happened.
When it happened.
Now, John had read, and he had heard read many times in Thessalonians, the fourth chapter of 1 Thessalonians,
that the Lord himself shall descend from heaven with a shout and with the voice of the archangel and the trump of God.
And John had contemplated for a little bit what that might mean.
And he had thought of a shout, and he had thought of a trump, and he had thought of the voice of the archangel,
but he did not realize nor did he dream that it would be like this when it happened.
There was a shout, but it was more than just a shout.
It ripped the air.
It pierced to the very center of the earth, to the very marrow of his bones.
And John had stopped everything.
And John Jones knew that this was it.
And he began to cry out,
Oh, no, Lord.
No, no, not yet.
I am not ready, Lord.
And then all at once, as if by magic instantaneously,
his heart had stopped beating.
And there had been a change.
His hands were cold and clammy and lifeless.
And in the wink of an eye, there had been a change come over him.
And half a block down the street, the Coca-Cola truck had wrecked, and it turned over.
And beverages were spilling out into the street.
And he thought, is the driver hurt?
And then he realized, what difference does it make if the driver is killed?
Everyone is killed, and yet everyone is still alive.
It was a state of emergency.
Everything was thrown into upheaval and chaos.
And suddenly there struck a cross of the day's mind of John Jones, one thought,
I must get home.
I must get home as quickly as I possibly can.
And he turned and began running down the same street that he had walked up just moments before.
But it seemed like an eternity, a lifetime ago.
And the white, neat, trimmed houses were rocking and reeling, and they were crumbling.
And as John passed that section of sidewalk that was cracked, broken,
he thought, what difference does that make now?
Because the whole street had opened up into a deep, wide-open chasm,
and cars and trees, and the auto, the car of the Williams boy and the Ingram girl tumbling down into it.
And John ran without hearing the sound of his steps,
but feeling the crude vibration of his feet pounding the sidewalk.
And he ran as hard as he could run.
And suddenly there arose across the vision of this man a spectacle that he could not believe.
He thought that he was imagining things.
And he told himself half-consciously,
I must watch and see if this happens again.
And suddenly there from the lawn of the Johnson family,
the ground opened up, and a body came slithering through the ground
and drifting into the air.
It was a judgment.
Bodies were coming from the ground all over,
and John ran as hard as he could run.
Now he could see the road slatteth on the porch of his little home.
He had to get home quickly.
Mary, Billy, and Susan is there.
Now he was there.
He turns up the walk and runs through the door that was open,
and he screams, Mary!
And there is no answer.
And groping blindly,
he fumbles down the hall to the bedroom,
and there's the bed empty, unmade.
Mary is gone.
And he started down the hall
and stumbled sprawling headlong across a piece of broken furniture,
and he raises and pulls himself up
and looks into Billy's room.
He's gone.
Susan is gone.
And he stumbled to the kitchen.
There was no Mary.
Dishes were broken.
The kitchen was in general disarray.
And there on the counter was a note that he had left Mary
telling her that he was walking to work,
that the car was in the garage,
and that there was a coffee pot that he had left on.
But Mary was gone.
And suddenly John Jones knew.
Mary was ready to go.
Billy and Susan were ready to go.
And then I am here all alone.
And then he thought,
Well, now, if they're gone,
I must go too,
because God said that,
Jesus said that all men shall be gathered before me,
before him.
And one thought waged itself into the numb mind of John Jones.
I must hide.
I cannot let God find me here.
And then he thought,
Where can I hide?
And then the basement.
He thought of the basement.
And he opened the door and thrust his body through
and fell sprawling to the basement floor
because the steps had broken away from the doorway.
And he felt something that was damp with his hands.
And it was a ruptured fuel tank.
And oil was on his hands.
And then he was horrified with the thought of fire.
What if a fire should happen?
And then ironically and bitterly,
John Jones began to laugh.
A fire, he thought.
Peter said that the world and all that is therein
shall be burnt up.
What difference will a hundred gallon of fuel oil make or not?
And he pulled himself to his knees
and began to crawl into a corner.
He must find some place to hide
because he is not ready to meet God.
And he put his face,
to crawl into a dark corner.
And he put his face into his hands
and he began to plead.
Please God.
Please cover me up.
Please let the house fall on me.
Why was I ever born?
Please God, let me die.
Let me become non-existent.
But there's one thing that John Jones never asked himself.
He never asked himself,
John Jones,
why have you waited so long to pray for God's help?
John, why didn't you obey your Lord a long time ago?
Why did you act and live as if your God did not exist?
Why did you act as if the Lord had been crucified
upon a totem pole instead of the cross of Calvary?
Why have you waited so long?
And John Jones,
don't you know that you would not have obeyed him
if he had given a thousand sons upon the cross
because you did not,
you would not have obeyed him
because you didn't love him enough,
you didn't believe him enough?
And as John Jones lay there babbling and crying
and begging for God's help and mercy,
suddenly he felt himself being lifted up into the air.
And he remembered that the Lord had said
that all nations shall be gathered before him
and they shall be judged.
And he remembered that Paul had said
in 2 Corinthians 5 chapter and the 10th verse
that we all shall appear before the judgment seat of Christ
and we shall be judged according to the things
that we have done in our body.
And suddenly from the basement,
the floor just opened up
and the ceiling folded itself away.
And by some unseen help,
the roof was flung from the house
and he felt himself going up, up.
And he closed his eyes and said,
I will not go, I will not look,
I will not face him.
And then he looked back at the earth at a distance
as the earth exploded.
Her plains, her beautiful rippled hills,
her gorgeous purple mountains,
her oceans, her deserts, her lands,
her houses, her wealth, her beauty,
her riches were all burning up.
And nothing was left.
And John Jones was going to judgment.
And as he approached, he closed his eyes.
But closed eyes could not close out the grandeur
of the beauty that he saw.
For just as John had said in Revelation,
the 20th chapter and the 11th verse,
he saw the dead, the great,
and the 11th verse,
and he saw before him the great white throne
and those,
and him that sat there on,
whose face the heavens and the earth fled away
and there was no place left for them.
And John Jones saw the dead,
the great and small,
standing before the throne of God.
And John looked,
and there was Mary,
and there was Billy,
and there was Susan.
They were on the right hand,
and John took his place
upon the left hand of the throne.
And he looked over horrified
upon the smiling face of his wife
and two lovely children.
And Mary turned and looked at him,
and she smiled.
And he could not hear her words say,
but he could see her lips say,
John, we love you.
We love you so much,
but we can't help you now.
You see, darling,
we just can't help you anymore.
And John Jones reaches out for his family,
and he could not move
because there was an awful kind of gravity
that kept him glued to his place.
And then his name was called John Jones.
And mechanically, reluctantly,
he moved forward,
and the books were opened.
And John Jones was judged,
and he was found guilty.
Not guilty of murder,
not guilty of adultery,
not guilty of drunkenness,
but he was guilty of neglect,
of the gift that God had given him,
guilty of thievery,
because he had stolen the grace and the goodness
and the blessings of God,
and he had given nothing in return.
He was guilty of turning his back upon the Lord,
of treading his blood-bought covenant under his feet.
John, you're guilty,
and you must pay for all of eternity.
And he felt himself being lifted up and hurled into outer space,
away from the presence of the great white throne,
and him that sat there on,
and he drifted down,
down, down,
to a horrible kind of a planet,
where there were real lakes and rivers
of steaming liquid fire,
scorched rocks,
incinerated earth.
And here John could hear the fringed howls of demons
and the curses of men.
He could see nothing,
he could feel nothing,
except the agony of the terrible loneliness
that he felt thrust into.
And he will remain upon this cursed planet
to run and to grope and to crawl and to cry out
and to fall for all of eternity
because he went to judgment without his Christ.
Now all of this is just a story.
It never happened.
Thank God it never happened.
But it will happen just as surely
as you're sitting here this morning,
just as surely as you're sitting here today,
unless you're in Jesus Christ,
unless you recognize your obligation to God
while you're living.
Now please listen to me.
Please listen to me this morning.
If you are outside of Jesus Christ's center,
listen to me today.
I want you to think.
I want you to think where you are
and what will be your light of this day
that should happen to you.
If this description's come true tomorrow morning,
I dare you to think
because if you think, you will act.
You think about where you stand with God today.
Oh, someone might say,
I wouldn't respond today
because just as surely as I walked down that aisle today,
someone would say,
look at that man, he's afraid.
Or look at that woman,
she's scared of all them things
that the preacher said.
Listen to me.
I didn't say the things that I said this morning to scare you.
I know that I believe that I know my own heart.
And I didn't say the things that I said to scare you.
But if you sit in your seat today
and walk out of this building
without confessing the wonderful life-giving name of Jesus Christ
and walk into the jaws of a never-ending eternity without God,
it is because you will not think.
You know, you might have many more opportunities
to hear the gospel preached,
and I hope and pray that you will.
But why should you?
Why should God give you many more opportunities?
Listen, today in this world,
there are people who have never heard the name of Jesus Christ mentioned,
and they will die without ever hearing the name of Jesus Christ mentioned.
And you have heard it over and over again.
Why has God been so good?
I must truthfully say I do not know.
But would you please think today,
would you think just enough
to know that God has had a purpose
in giving you all of these opportunities?
Will you come today believing that Jesus Christ is the Son of God,
repenting, which is a change of mind,
turning away from serving the world
to wanting to serve and please God?
Will you come confessing that faith
that you believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God?
Will you come being baptized in Him to wash away your sins,
being made one with Him,
added to His body, His church?
If you are here and subject to this invitation,
we pray that you will come.
We plead that you will come this morning.
Now, if you're here this morning
and once done these things
and remain faithful for a while
but wander back into the beggarly elements of the world,
we plead with you to come this morning.
You don't want to be found on the left hand of the throne of God
at the day of judgment.
If you have ever back into the ways of the world,
I know that you want to be on the right hand of the throne also.
If you're here this morning
and subject to the invitation,
then you need to come repenting,
confessing,
and asking the prayers of the church
that your sins might be forgiven,
that you might be added back into the fold.
If you're here subject to the invitation,
will you not come at this time
while we stand and sing the invitation?
Give me your hand and God your heart.
There's a great day coming,
a great day coming,
there's a great day coming,